<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>A. Simaz Bunzel</title><link>https://asimazbunzel.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on A. Simaz Bunzel</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://asimazbunzel.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>About</title><link>https://asimazbunzel.github.io/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 14:32:13 -0300</pubDate><guid>https://asimazbunzel.github.io/about/</guid><description>My interests involve:
Stellar evolution of massive binaries
The main topic of my research as a PhD student involves the study of the binary evolution of progenitors of double compact objects which are the sources of gravitational waves that the LIGO/Virgo collaboration is currently detecting
Final stages of stellar evolution
I am also interested in the study of powerful transients connected to the end points of stellar-evolution of massive stars, such as Supernovae.</description><content>&lt;p>My interests involve:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Stellar evolution of massive binaries&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The main topic of my research as a PhD student involves the study of the binary evolution of
progenitors of double compact objects which are the sources of gravitational waves that the
LIGO/Virgo collaboration is currently detecting&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Final stages of stellar evolution&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I am also interested in the study of powerful transients connected to the end points of
stellar-evolution of massive stars, such as Supernovae. In addition to this, its role is extremely
important for progenitors of gravitational waves as asymmetries happening during this transient
phenomena can change the parameters of the binary&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Technology misc&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Apart from science, I like to code on my free time whatever I feel like. Most of the things I code
can be found in my &lt;a href="https://github.com/asimazbunzel">GitHub profile&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Contact&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>email: &lt;a href="mailto:asimazbunzel@gmail.com">asimazbunzel@gmail.com&lt;/a>&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>CV</title><link>https://asimazbunzel.github.io/cv/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 14:32:13 -0300</pubDate><guid>https://asimazbunzel.github.io/cv/</guid><description>TBD</description><content>&lt;p>TBD&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>Evolution of eccentric high-mass X-ray binaries. The case of GX 301-2</title><link>https://asimazbunzel.github.io/academics/gx301/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://asimazbunzel.github.io/academics/gx301/</guid><description>In this work, we explore a large set of stellar-evolution models aim at reproducing current measurements of this very rare binary. special attention is put on the core-collapse and the assymetries happening at that moment as it seems they are needed to explain what the binary looks nowadays.
A GitHub repository contains all the source code to produce the raw data as well as scripts to reproduce all the figures in the manuscript.</description><content>&lt;p>In this work, we explore a large set of stellar-evolution models aim at
reproducing current measurements of this very rare binary. special attention is put on the
core-collapse and the assymetries happening at that moment as it seems they are needed to explain
what the binary looks nowadays.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>A GitHub repository contains all the source code to produce the raw data as well as scripts to
reproduce all the figures in the manuscript. I strongly support a reproducible science approach&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Link to the paper: &lt;a href="https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022arxiv221211881s/abstract">astrophysics data system&lt;/a> (FREE)&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Zenodo repository: &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/record/7261481">GX 301-2&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></content></item><item><title>Impact of tides on non-coplanar orbits of progenitors of high-mass X-ray binaries</title><link>https://asimazbunzel.github.io/academics/tides/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://asimazbunzel.github.io/academics/tides/</guid><description>An interesting topic regarding the role of tides (like the ones acting on the oceans due to the moon and the earth not being a solid body) on binaries containing a common-type star and a compact-object (neutron star or black hole). it turns out, they are very important in predicting a lot of stellar (and binary) parameters !
A GitHub repository contains all the source code to produce the raw data as well as scripts to reproduce all the figures in the manuscript.</description><content>&lt;p>An interesting topic regarding the role of tides (like the ones acting on the oceans due to the
moon and the earth not being a solid body) on binaries containing a common-type star and a
compact-object (neutron star or black hole). it turns out, they are very important in predicting a
lot of stellar (and binary) parameters !&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>A GitHub repository contains all the source code to produce the raw data as well as scripts to
reproduce all the figures in the manuscript. I strongly support a reproducible science approach&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Link to the paper: &lt;a href="https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2023A%26A...670A..45S/abstract">astrophysics data system&lt;/a> (FREE)&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></content></item><item><title>Progenitors of low-mass binary black-hole mergers in the isolated binary evolution scenario</title><link>https://asimazbunzel.github.io/academics/lowmassbbh/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://asimazbunzel.github.io/academics/lowmassbbh/</guid><description>We explore various stellar parameters which produce low-mass binary black-holes. These binaries were first detected by the gravitational waves interferometers of LIGO and Virgo !
A GitHub repository contains all the source code to produce the raw data as well as scripts to reproduce all the figures in the manuscript. I strongly support a reproducible science approach
Link to the paper: astrophysics data system (FREE)</description><content>&lt;p>We explore various stellar parameters which produce low-mass binary black-holes. These binaries
were first detected by the gravitational waves interferometers of LIGO and Virgo !&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>A GitHub repository contains all the source code to produce the raw data as well as scripts to
reproduce all the figures in the manuscript. I strongly support a reproducible science approach&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Link to the paper: &lt;a href="https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021A%26A...649A.114G/abstract">astrophysics data system&lt;/a> (FREE)&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></content></item><item><title>Some more contributions</title><link>https://asimazbunzel.github.io/academics/more/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://asimazbunzel.github.io/academics/more/</guid><description>I have participated in several other works:
A catalogue of high-mass X-ray binaries in the Galaxy: from the INTEGRAL to the Gaia era &amp;raquo; This is an online catalog of high-mass X-ray binaries with the advantage over previous ones in that it is actively maintained by a team using GitHub pages.
Interaction of a high-mass X-ray binary with the interstellar medium through stellar wind. The case of GX 301-2 &amp;raquo; My contribution in this work is related to the stellar-evolution model of a progenitor for the binary.</description><content>&lt;p>I have participated in several other works:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2023arXiv230202656F/abstract">A catalogue of high-mass X-ray binaries in the Galaxy: from the INTEGRAL to the Gaia era&lt;/a> &amp;raquo; This is an online catalog of high-mass
X-ray binaries with the advantage over previous ones in that it is actively maintained by a team
using GitHub pages.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022arXiv221206623M/abstract">Interaction of a high-mass X-ray binary with the interstellar medium through stellar wind. The case of GX 301-2&lt;/a> &amp;raquo; My contribution
in this work is related to the stellar-evolution model of a progenitor for the binary. Here the
focus is set on the contribution of the high-mass X-ray binary to pollute the medium with gas to
trigger stellar formation.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022A%26A...665A..31F/abstract">Constraints to neutron-star kicks in high-mass X-ray binaries with Gaia EDR3&lt;/a> &amp;raquo; Statistical study of natal kicks produced during
the end point in the stellar-evolution of massive stars in progenitors of high-mass X-ray binaries.
Interesingly, we find a more complex distribution for the natal kicks produced due to the
assymetries, than those find in isolated pulsars !&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021ApJ...909..145D/abstract">SN 2013ai: A Link between Hydrogen-rich and Hydrogen-poor Core-collapse Supernovae&lt;/a> &amp;raquo; My contribution included a stellar-evolution
model for the progenitor system. The work is much more complete with lots of analysis of
observational data !&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022ATel15638....1Z/abstract">Confirmation of glitch event observed in PSR J0742-2822 at the Argentine Institute of Radioastronomy (IAR)&lt;/a> &amp;raquo; Astronomy telegram
with a glitch event of a known pulsar. Data taken from @IAR !&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021ApJ...908..158S/abstract">PSR J0437-4715: The Argentine Institute of Radioastronomy 2019-2020 Observational Campaign&lt;/a> &amp;raquo; Analysis of radio observations taken
with the two (radio) telescopes located @IAR (my workplace !)&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></content></item></channel></rss>