<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://asimazbunzel.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://asimazbunzel.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-04-06T10:14:26-07:00</updated><id>https://asimazbunzel.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">A. S. B.</title><subtitle>Ms.S in Astronomy</subtitle><author><name>Adolfo Simaz Bunzel</name><email>asimazbunzel@iar.unlp.edu.ar</email></author><entry><title type="html">Paper notes: Different to the core: the pre-supernova structures of massive single and binary-stripped stars</title><link href="https://asimazbunzel.github.io/posts/2021/02/blog-post-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paper notes: Different to the core: the pre-supernova structures of massive single and binary-stripped stars" /><published>2021-02-22T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-22T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://asimazbunzel.github.io/posts/2021/02/laplace-et-al-2021</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asimazbunzel.github.io/posts/2021/02/blog-post-2/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abstract&lt;/em&gt;: The majority of massive stars live in binary or multiple systems and will interact
during their lifetimes, which helps to explain the observed diversity of core-collapse supernovae.
Donor stars in binary systems can lose most of their hydrogen-rich envelopes through mass transfer,
which not only affects the surface properties, but also the core structure. However, most
calculations of the core-collapse properties of massive stars rely on single-star models. We present
a systematic study of the difference between the pre-supernova structures of single stars and stars
of the same initial mass (11 - 21 M&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;_\odot&lt;/script&gt;) that have been stripped due to stable post-main
sequence mass transfer at solar metallicity. We present the pre-supernova core composition with novel
diagrams that give an intuitive representation of the isotope distribution. As shown in previous
studies, at the edge of the carbon-oxygen core, the binary-stripped star models contain an extended
gradient of carbon, oxygen, and neon. This layer originates from the receding of the convective helium
core during core helium burning in binary-stripped stars, which does not occur in single-star models.
We find that this same evolutionary phase leads to systematic differences in the final density and
nuclear energy generation profiles. Binary-stripped star models have systematically higher total
masses of carbon at the moment of core collapse compared to single star models, which likely results
in systematically different supernova yields. In about half of our models, the silicon-burning and
oxygen-rich layers merge after core silicon burning. We discuss the implications of our findings for
the explodability, supernova observations, and nucleosynthesis from these stars. Our models will be
publicly available and can be readily used as input for supernova simulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authors: E. Laplace, S. Justham, M. Renzo, Y. Gotberg, R. Farmer, D. Vartanyan, S. E. de Mink&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2102.05036&quot;&gt;Arxiv link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-intro&quot;&gt;1. Intro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Massive stars are found in binaries, interaction becomes &lt;strong&gt;almost&lt;/strong&gt; unavoidable (Sana et al., etc.).
The final outcome would then be different to a single massive star, something very important for
e.g., the population of compact-objects binaries. &lt;strong&gt;However, most of current studies do not consider
binary evolution but rather a pure He-star or removing mass through a wind sometime in the evolution
of single stars&lt;/strong&gt;. Also, binary studies stops much earlier in the evolution: typically at core C
depletion, with a little nuclear reaction network due to computational limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work: detailed evolution of single and binaries with masses 11 - 21 M&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;_\odot&lt;/script&gt;, until core
collapse, with a 128 isotopes nuclear reaction network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aim: comparison of pre-collapse interior structures, composition. Implications, limitations, …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-method&quot;&gt;2. Method&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evolution with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;{\tt MESA}&lt;/script&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;single stars between 11 - 21 M&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;_\odot&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;close binaries with primaries between 11 - 21 M&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;_\odot&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P_{\rm orb} =&lt;/script&gt; 25 - 35 days, aim at
studying stable case B of mass-transfer (MT). Companion is a compact-object with $q =$ 0.8 (fixed)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-comparison-between-single-vs-binary-models&quot;&gt;3. Comparison between single vs binary models&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/laplace2021-figure1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Point C (half of core-He burning): no H-rich shell in binary due to MT. Core of donor in binary is
cooler but denser, behaves as a the core of a less massive initial star&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Point D (end of core-He burning): larger core mass for single model. Different core C/O ratios. In
binary model there is a C/O gradient in the edge of the core due to wind mass-loss&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Point E (end of core-C burning): different O/Ne abundances due to different initial conditions and
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\rho_{\rm c}&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_{\rm c}&lt;/script&gt; values&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Point F (end of core-O burning): core composition very different really close to core-collapse&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-differences-between-single-vs-binary-models&quot;&gt;4. Differences between single vs binary models&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare models at core-collapse with same core-masses as explosions are related to core properties&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;41-composition&quot;&gt;4.1 Composition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/laplace2021-figure2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Region I: binaries have a a C/O gradient, singles don’t. Related to convective core shrinking at
core He burning (mass-loss)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Region II: similar composition, different abundances. Shell mergers in 4.3 M&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;_\odot&lt;/script&gt; models.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Region III: higher mass-fractions of Si around Fe core.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;42-shell-mergers&quot;&gt;4.2 Shell mergers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some models the layer burning Si merges with an O-rich shell producing more Si, S, Ar and Ca, and
reducing O, Ne, Mg. This Ca is important as it could be used as an observational test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Question: Is this merger a numerical artifact due to the prescription used for convection ?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;43-final-total-massses-of-isotopes&quot;&gt;4.3 Final total massses of isotopes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Less He in binaries due to winds and MT interactions&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;More C in binaries&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Similar O and Fe&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;44-density-profiles&quot;&gt;4.4 Density profiles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/laplace2021-figure6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 6&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Region I (He-rich layer): higher densities in binary models, steeper profile at the outer edge.
Shallow drop in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mu&lt;/script&gt; due to the presence of a C/O gradient&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Region II (O-rich layer): small peak in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mu&lt;/script&gt; conected to Si-rich layer. Large difference in
densities&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For single stars, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mu&lt;/script&gt; increases in the outer layers thanks to the recombination&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;45-he-core-properties&quot;&gt;4.5 He core properties&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Larger He core radius in binaries compare to single stars. This radius decreases for higher masses&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-origins-of-differences&quot;&gt;5. Origins of differences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;51-chemical-gradient&quot;&gt;5.1 Chemical gradient&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In single stars, the grow of the convective core brings new He that favors alpha-captures onto C
thus increasing the mass fraction of O. The exact opposite happens the donor of a binary where
instead there is a decrease in size of the convective core due to stellar winds. This receding
core is also responsible for the C/O gradient found in binary models just outside the He-depleted
core&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a difference in the density and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mu&lt;/script&gt; profile between the star and binary models
mostly found outside the He-depleted core, related to the presence (or absence) of the C/O gradient&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;52-final-total-isotope-masses&quot;&gt;5.2 Final total isotope masses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Related to the rates of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\alpha&lt;/script&gt;-captures and triple-&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\alpha&lt;/script&gt; reaction after core-He burning,
i.e., shell He burning and so on&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;53-shell-burning&quot;&gt;5.3 Shell burning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/laplace2021-figure12.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 12&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He rich layer is denser in the binary model, starts after core-He depletion, thus, during the
ignition of He in a shell&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/laplace2021-figure13.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 13&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Point D (end of core-He burning): in single model there is a H-burning shell and a strong
He-burning shell. In binary, no H shell and faint He-burning shell&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Point E (end of core-C burning): extended He-burning shell in binary, but weaker in power than
for the single model. In binary model, there is more C which in turn introduces more
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\alpha&lt;/script&gt;-captures (exactly the opposite to what happens in core-He burning)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Point F (end of core-O burning): C-burning shell location is different due to an increment
in the C mass fraction for the binary model which allows this layer to ignite further out&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defining the mass of the future compact-object as the mass inside the star with an specific
entropy below 4 erg g&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;^{-1}&lt;/script&gt; K&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;^{-1}&lt;/script&gt;, they derive a compact object mass of 1.83 M&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;_\odot&lt;/script&gt;
for the single model and 1.9 M&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;_\odot&lt;/script&gt; for the binary&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;54-compactness-evolution&quot;&gt;5.4 Compactness evolution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/laplace2021-figure14.png&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 14&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At core-collapse, binary models have lower compactness values than single stars with the same
initial mass, but these numbers are similar when comparing similar core masses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;discussion&quot;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Due to the differences in the compactness of stars with the same initial masses but in single
and binary models, binaries might explore more easily (though, based on pure He stars, this
has not been found in multi-D simulations). But considering the changes in the interior
profiles, this might hint for a change in this&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Composition is certainly different in single and binary models. This can lead to different
nucleosynthesis in the supernova stage which can be observed, e.g., during the nebular stage
by measuring O lines (used to derived an estimation of the pre core-collapse masses of the
stars)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wind-mass loss, responsible for the C/O gradient outside the He-depleted core of binaries, is
highly uncertain and can, in principle, affect both the core composition at late stages and
the density structure pre-supernova. Have implications in the derived core masses and, with
it, in the compact object masses&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Convection and shell mergers still debated. Changes abundances in the star, so nucleosynthesis
at supernova is affected by it&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Adolfo Simaz Bunzel</name><email>asimazbunzel@iar.unlp.edu.ar</email></author><category term="research" /><category term="stellar evolution" /><category term="close binaries" /><summary type="html">Abstract: The majority of massive stars live in binary or multiple systems and will interact during their lifetimes, which helps to explain the observed diversity of core-collapse supernovae. Donor stars in binary systems can lose most of their hydrogen-rich envelopes through mass transfer, which not only affects the surface properties, but also the core structure. However, most calculations of the core-collapse properties of massive stars rely on single-star models. We present a systematic study of the difference between the pre-supernova structures of single stars and stars of the same initial mass (11 - 21 M) that have been stripped due to stable post-main sequence mass transfer at solar metallicity. We present the pre-supernova core composition with novel diagrams that give an intuitive representation of the isotope distribution. As shown in previous studies, at the edge of the carbon-oxygen core, the binary-stripped star models contain an extended gradient of carbon, oxygen, and neon. This layer originates from the receding of the convective helium core during core helium burning in binary-stripped stars, which does not occur in single-star models. We find that this same evolutionary phase leads to systematic differences in the final density and nuclear energy generation profiles. Binary-stripped star models have systematically higher total masses of carbon at the moment of core collapse compared to single star models, which likely results in systematically different supernova yields. In about half of our models, the silicon-burning and oxygen-rich layers merge after core silicon burning. We discuss the implications of our findings for the explodability, supernova observations, and nucleosynthesis from these stars. Our models will be publicly available and can be readily used as input for supernova simulations.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Who I am</title><link href="https://asimazbunzel.github.io/posts/2021/02/blog-post-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who I am" /><published>2021-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://asimazbunzel.github.io/posts/2021/02/first-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asimazbunzel.github.io/posts/2021/02/blog-post-1/">&lt;p&gt;See my codes in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/AdolfoSimazBunzel&quot;&gt;github user&lt;/a&gt;.
Also, more on my person at &lt;a href=&quot;https://garra.iar.unlp.edu.ar/people/adolfo.html&quot;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Adolfo Simaz Bunzel</name><email>asimazbunzel@iar.unlp.edu.ar</email></author><category term="welcome" /><summary type="html">See my codes in my github user. Also, more on my person at this link</summary></entry></feed>